<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- 
   Copyright 2004 The Apache Software Foundation

   Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
   you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
   You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.2//EN" "./dtd/document-v12.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY projectroot '../'>
  <!ENTITY % common-links SYSTEM "../links.ent">
  %common-links;
]>
<document>

  <header>
    <title>Panorama Startup</title>
  </header>
  
  <body>
<p>
Panorama is a disguised version of
<link href="http://www.webct.com/">WebCT</link>'s <strong>Vista</strong> application.  Vista is
a truly massive web application, consisting of thousands of Java classes and JSPs and hundreds of EJBs. Vista is
organized as a large number of somewhat interrelated <em>tools</em> with an underlying substrate of <em>services</em>.
In fact, HiveMind was originally created to manage the complexity of Vista.
</p>   

<note>
The reality is that Vista, a commercial project, has continued with an older version of HiveMind. Panorama
is based on original code in Vista, but has been altered to take advantage of many features available
in more recent versions of HiveMind. Keeping the names seperate keeps us honest about the differences between a
product actually in production (Vista) versus an idealized version used for demonstration and tutorial purposes (Panorama).
</note> 

<p>
With all these interrelated tools and services, the simple act of starting up the application was complex.  Many
tools and services have <em>startup operations</em>, things that need to occur when the application first starts
up within the application server. For example, the help service reads and caches help text stored within the database.
The mail service creates periodic jobs to peform database garbage collection of deleted mail items.  All told, Vista had
over 40 different tasks to perform at startup ... many with subtle dependencies (such as the mail tool
needing the job scheduler service to be up and running).
</p>

<p>
The <em>legacy</em> version of Vista startup consisted of a WebLogic startup class that invoked a 
central stateless session EJB. The startup EJB was responsible for performing all 40+ startup tasks ... typically
by invoking a public static method of a class related to the tool.
</p>

<p>
This was problematic for several reasons. It created a dependency on WebLogic to manage startup (really, a minor consideration,
but one nonetheless). More importantly, it created an unnecessary binding between the startup EJB and all the other code
in all the other tools. These unwanted dependencies created ripple effects throughout the code base that impacted
refactored efforts, and caused deployment problems that complicated the build (requiring the duplication of
many common classes inside the startup EJB's JAR, to resolve runtime classloader dependencies).
</p>

<note>
It's all about class loaders. The class loader that loaded the startup EJB didn't have visibility to the contents
of the other EJB JARs deployed within the Vista EAR. To satisfy WebLogic's ejbc command (EJB JAR packaging tool),
and to succesfully locate the classes at runtime, it was necessary to duplicate many classes from the other EJB JARs into the startup EJB JAR.
With HiveMind, this issue goes away, since the module deployment descriptors store the class <em>name</em>, and the
<em>servlet thread's context class loader</em> is used to resolve that name ... and <em>it</em> has visibility
to all the classes in all the EJB JARs.
</note>

<section>
  <title>Enter HiveMind</title>
  
<p>
HiveMind's ultimate purpose was to simplify all aspects of Vista development and create a simpler, faster,
more robust development environment. The first step on this journey, a trial step, was to rationalize the startup process.
</p>  

<p>
Each startup task would be given a unique id, a title and a set of <em>dependencies</em> (on other tasks). How
the task actually operated was left quite abstract ... with careful support for supporting the existing legacy approach
(public static methods). What would change would be how these tasks were executed.
</p>

<p>
The advantage of HiveMind is that each <em>module</em> can contribute as many or as few startup tasks
as necessary into the Startup configuration point as needed. This allows the startup logic to be
properly <em>encapsulated</em> in the module. The startup logic can be easily changed without affecting
other modules, and without having to change any single contentious resource (such as the legacy approach's
startup EJB).
</p>

</section>

<section>
  <title>Startup task schema</title>

<p>
The schema for startup tasks contributions must support the explicit ordering of execution based on dependencies.
With HiveMind, there's no telling in what order modules will be processed, and so no telling in what order
contributions will appear within a configuration point ... so it is necessary to make ordering explicit
by giving each task a unique id, and listing dependencies (the ids of tasks that must precede, or must
follow, any single task).
</p>

<p>
Special consideration was given to supporting legacy startup code in the tools and services; code that stays
in the form of a public static method.  As HiveMind is adopted, these static methods will go away, and be replaced
with either HiveMind services, or simple objects. In the very long term, much of this startup logic will become uncessary,
as more of the system will be implemented using HiveMind services, which will lazily initialize just as needed.
</p>
  
<p>
The schema definition (with desriptions removed, for compactness) follows:
</p>  

<source><![CDATA[
<schema id="Tasks">
  <element name="task">
    <attribute name="title" required="true"/>
    <attribute name="id" required="true"/>
    <attribute name="before"/>
    <attribute name="after"/>      
    <attribute name="executable" required="true" translator="object"/>
      
    <conversion class="com.panorama.startup.impl.Task"/>
  </element>
  
  <element name="static-task">
    <attribute name="title" required="true"/>
    <attribute name="id" required="true"/>
    <attribute name="before"/>
    <attribute name="after"/>           
    <attribute name="class" translator="class" required="true"/>
    <attribute name="method"/>
      
    <rules>
      <create-object class="com.panorama.startup.impl.Task"/>
      <invoke-parent method="addElement"/>
        
      <read-attribute attribute="id" property="id"/>
      <read-attribute attribute="title" property="title"/>
      <read-attribute attribute="before" property="before"/>
      <read-attribute attribute="after" property="after"/>
        
      <create-object class="com.panorama.startup.impl.ExecuteStatic"/>
      <invoke-parent method="setExecutable"/>
        
      <read-attribute attribute="class" property="targetClass"/>
      <read-attribute attribute="method" property="methodName"/>       
    </rules>
  </element>
</schema>]]></source>

<note>
For more details, see <link href="hivedocs/schema/panorama.startup.Tasks.html">the HiveDoc for
  the Tasks schema</link>.
</note>

<p>
This schema supports contributions in two formats.  The first format allows an arbitrary object or 
service to be contributed:
</p>

<source><![CDATA[
<task id="mail" title="Mail" executable="service:MailStartup"/>]]></source>

<p>
The <code>executable</code> attribute is converted into an object or service; here the <code>service:</code>
prefix indicates that the rest of the string, <code>MailStartup</code>, is a service id
(other prefixes are defined by the &hivemind.ObjectProviders; configuration). If this task
has dependencies, the <code>before</code> and <code>after</code> attributes can be specified as well.
</p>

<p>
To support legacy code, a second option, <code>static-task</code>, is provided:
</p>
<source><![CDATA[
<static-task id="discussions" title="Discussions" after="mail" class="com.panorama.discussions.DiscussionsStartup"/>]]></source>

<p>
The <code>static-task</code> element duplicates the <code>id</code>, <code>title</code>,
<code>before</code> and <code>after</code> attributes, but replaces <code>executable</code>
with <code>class</code> (the name of the class containing the method) and
<code>method</code> (the name of the method to invoke, defaulting to "init").
</p>
</section>


<section>
  <title>Startup Service</title>

<p>
  The schema just defines what contributions <em>look like</em> and how they are converted
  to objects; we need to define a Startup configuration point using the schema, and
  a Startup service that uses the configuration point.
</p>  

<source><![CDATA[
<configuration-point id="Startup" schema-id="Tasks"/>

<service-point id="Startup" interface="java.lang.Runnable">
  <invoke-factory>
    <construct class="com.panorama.startup.impl.TaskExecutor">
      <set-configuration property="tasks" configuration-id="Startup"/>
    </construct>
  </invoke-factory>
</service-point>

<contribution id="hivemind.Startup">
  <startup object="service:Startup"/>
</contribution>]]></source>
  

<p>
The <code>hivemind.Startup</code> configuration point is used to ensure that the Panorama Startup service is
executed when the Registry itself is constructed.
</p>

</section>

<section>
  <title>Implementation</title>
  
<p>
All that remains is the implementations of the service and task classes.
</p>  

<section>
  <title>Executable.java</title>

<source><![CDATA[package com.panorama.startup;

/**
 * Much like {@link java.lang.Runnable}, but allows the caller
 * to handle any exceptions thrown.
 *
 * @author Howard Lewis Ship
 */
public interface Executable
{
    public void execute() throws Exception;
}]]></source>

<p>
The Executable interface is implemented by tasks, and by services or other objects that need to
be executed.  It <code>throws Exception</code> so that exception catching and reporting can be
centralized inside the Startup service.
</p>


</section>

<section>
  <title>Task.java</title>
  
<source><![CDATA[package com.panorama.startup.impl;

import org.apache.hivemind.impl.BaseLocatable;

import com.panorama.startup.Executable;

/**
 * An operation that may be executed. A Task exists to wrap
 * an {@link com.panorama.startup.Executable} object with
 * a title and ordering information (id, after, before).
 *
 * @author Howard Lewis Ship
 */
public class Task extends BaseLocatable implements Executable
{
    private String _id;
    private String _title;
    private String _after;
    private String _before;
    private Executable _executable;

    public String getBefore()
    {
        return _before;
    }

    public String getId()
    {
        return _id;
    }

    public String getAfter()
    {
        return _after;
    }

    public String getTitle()
    {
        return _title;
    }

    public void setExecutable(Executable executable)
    {
        _executable = executable;
    }

    public void setBefore(String string)
    {
        _before = string;
    }

    public void setId(String string)
    {
        _id = string;
    }

    public void setAfter(String string)
    {
        _after = string;
    }

    public void setTitle(String string)
    {
        _title = string;
    }

    /**
     * Delegates to the {@link #setExecutable(Executable) executable} object.
     */
    public void execute() throws Exception
    {
        _executable.execute();
    }

}
]]></source>  

<p>
The Task class is a wrapper around an Executable object; whether that's a service, some arbitrary object,
or a StaticTask.
</p>

</section>

<section>
  <title>ExecuteStatic.java</title>


<source><![CDATA[package com.panorama.startup.impl;

import java.lang.reflect.Method;

import com.panorama.startup.Executable;

/**
 * Used to access the legacy startup code that is in the form
 * of a public static method (usually <code>init()</code>) on some
 * class.
 *
 * @author Howard Lewis Ship
 */
public class ExecuteStatic implements Executable
{
    private String _methodName = "init";
    private Class _targetClass;

    public void execute() throws Exception
    {
        Method m = _targetClass.getMethod(_methodName, null);

        m.invoke(null, null);
    }

    /**
     * Sets the name of the method to invoke; if not set, the default is <code>init</code>.
     * The target class must have a public static method with that name taking no
     * parameters.
     */
    public void setMethodName(String string)
    {
        _methodName = string;
    }

    /**
     * Sets the class to invoke the method on.
     */
    public void setTargetClass(Class targetClass)
    {
        _targetClass = targetClass;
    }
}
]]></source>

<p>
ExecuteStatic uses Java reflection to invoke a public static method of a particular class.
</p>

</section>

<section>
  <title>TaskExecutor.java</title>
  
<source><![CDATA[package com.panorama.startup.impl;

import java.util.Iterator;
import java.util.List;

import org.apache.commons.logging.Log;
import org.apache.hivemind.ErrorHandler;
import org.apache.hivemind.Messages;
import org.apache.hivemind.order.Orderer;

/**
 * A service that executes a series of {@link com.panorama.startup.impl.Task}s. Tasks have
 * an ordering based on pre- and post-requisites.
 *
 * @author Howard Lewis Ship
 */
public class TaskExecutor implements Runnable
{
    private ErrorHandler _errorHandler;
    private Log _log;
    private List _tasks;
    private Messages _messages;

    /**
     * Orders the {@link #setTasks(List) tasks} into an execution order, and executes
     * each in turn.  Logs the elapsed time, number of tasks, and the number of failures (if any).
     */
    public void run()
    {
        long startTime = System.currentTimeMillis();
 
        Orderer orderer = new Orderer(_log, _errorHandler, task());

        Iterator i = _tasks.iterator();
        while (i.hasNext())
        {
            Task t = (Task) i.next();

            orderer.add(t, t.getId(), t.getAfter(), t.getBefore());
        }

        List orderedTasks = orderer.getOrderedObjects();

        int failures = 0;

        i = orderedTasks.iterator();
        while (i.hasNext())
        {
            Task t = (Task) i.next();

            if (!execute(t))
                failures++;
        }

        long elapsedTime = System.currentTimeMillis() - startTime;

        if (failures == 0)
            _log.info(success(orderedTasks.size(), elapsedTime));
        else
            _log.info(failure(failures, orderedTasks.size(), elapsedTime));
    }

    /**
     * Execute a single task.
     * 
     * @return true on success, false on failure
     */
    private boolean execute(Task t)
    {
        _log.info(executingTask(t));

        try
        {
            t.execute();

            return true;
        }
        catch (Exception ex)
        {
            _errorHandler.error(_log, exceptionInTask(t, ex), t.getLocation(), ex);

            return false;
        }
    }

    private String task()
    {
        return _messages.getMessage("task");
    }

    private String executingTask(Task t)
    {
        return _messages.format("executing-task", t.getTitle());
    }

    private String exceptionInTask(Task t, Throwable cause)
    {
        return _messages.format("exception-in-task", t.getTitle(), cause);
    }

    private String success(int count, long elapsedTimeMillis)
    {
        return _messages.format("success", new Integer(count), new Long(elapsedTimeMillis));
    }

    private String failure(int failureCount, int totalCount, long elapsedTimeMillis)
    {
        return _messages.format(
            "failure",
            new Integer(failureCount),
            new Integer(totalCount),
            new Long(elapsedTimeMillis));
    }

    public void setErrorHandler(ErrorHandler handler)
    {
        _errorHandler = handler;
    }

    public void setLog(Log log)
    {
        _log = log;
    }

    public void setMessages(Messages messages)
    {
        _messages = messages;
    }

    public void setTasks(List list)
    {
        _tasks = list;
    }

}]]></source>
  
<p>
This class is where it all comes together; it is the core service implementation for the
<code>panorama.startup.Startup</code>  service.  It is constructed by the &hivemind.BuilderFactory;, which
autowires the <code>errorHandler</code>, <code>log</code> and <code>messages</code> properties, as
well as the <code>tasks</code> property (which is explicitly set in the module deployment descriptor).
</p>  


<p>
  Most of the <code>run()</code> method is concerned with ordering the contributed tasks into
  execution order and reporting the results. 
</p>
  
</section>

</section>

<section>
  <title>Unit Testing</title>
  
<p>
Unit testing in HiveMind is accomplished by <em>acting like the container</em>; that is, your code
is responsible for instantiating the core service implementation and setting its properties.  In many cases,
you will set the properties to mock objects ... HiveMind uses
<link href="http://www.easymock.org/">EasyMock</link> extensively, and
provides a base class, <code>HiveMindTestCase</code>, that contains much support for creating Mock controls
and objects.
</p>

<section>
  <title>TestTaskExcecutor.java</title>
</section>

<source><![CDATA[package com.panorama.startup.impl;

import java.util.ArrayList;
import java.util.Collections;
import java.util.List;
import java.util.Locale;

import org.apache.commons.logging.Log;
import org.apache.hivemind.ApplicationRuntimeException;
import org.apache.hivemind.ErrorHandler;
import org.apache.hivemind.Messages;
import org.apache.hivemind.Resource;
import org.apache.hivemind.impl.MessagesImpl;
import org.apache.hivemind.test.ExceptionAwareArgumentsMatcher;
import org.apache.hivemind.test.HiveMindTestCase;
import org.apache.hivemind.test.RegexpArgumentsMatcher;
import org.apache.hivemind.util.FileResource;
import org.easymock.MockControl;

import com.panorama.startup.Executable;

/**
 * Tests for the {@link com.panorama.startup.impl.TaskExecutor} service.
 *
 * @author Howard Lewis Ship
 */
public class TestTaskExecutor extends HiveMindTestCase
{
    private static List _tokens = new ArrayList();

    protected void setUp()
    {
        _tokens.clear();
    }

    protected void tearDown()
    {
        _tokens.clear();
    }

    public static void addToken(String token)
    {
        _tokens.add(token);
    }

    public Messages getMessages()
    {
      . . .
    }

    public void testSuccess()
    {
        ExecutableFixture f1 = new ExecutableFixture("f1");

        Task t1 = new Task();

        t1.setExecutable(f1);
        t1.setId("first");
        t1.setAfter("second");
        t1.setTitle("Fixture #1");

        ExecutableFixture f2 = new ExecutableFixture("f2");

        Task t2 = new Task();
        t2.setExecutable(f2);
        t2.setId("second");
        t2.setTitle("Fixture #2");

        List tasks = new ArrayList();
        tasks.add(t1);
        tasks.add(t2);

        MockControl logControl = newControl(Log.class);
        Log log = (Log) logControl.getMock();

        TaskExecutor e = new TaskExecutor();

        ErrorHandler errorHandler = (ErrorHandler) newMock(ErrorHandler.class);

        e.setErrorHandler(errorHandler);
        e.setLog(log);
        e.setMessages(getMessages());
        e.setTasks(tasks);

        // Note the ordering; explicitly set, to check that ordering does
        // take place.
        log.info("Executing task Fixture #2.");
        log.info("Executing task Fixture #1.");
        log.info("Executed 2 tasks \\(in \\d+ milliseconds\\)\\.");
        logControl.setMatcher(new RegexpArgumentsMatcher());

        replayControls();

        e.run();

        assertListsEqual(new String[] { "f2", "f1" }, _tokens);

        verifyControls();
    }

}
]]></source>  
 
<p>
In this listing (which is a paired down version of the real class), you can see how 
mock objects, including EasyMock objects, are used. The ExecutableFixture classes will invoke
the <code>addToken()</code> method; the point is to provide, in the tasks List,
those fixtures wrapped in Task objects and see that they are invoked in the correct order.
</p>

<p>
We create a Mock Log object, and check that the correct messages are logged in the correct order.  Once
we have set the expectations for all the EasyMock controls, we invoke <code>replayControls()</code> and
continue with our test.  The <code>verifyControls()</code> method ensures that all mock objects
have had all expected methods invoked on them.
</p>

<p>
That's just <em>unit</em> testing; you always want to supplement that with <em>integration</em>
testing ... to ensure, at the very least, that your schema is valid, the conversion rules work, and the contributions
are correct.  However, as the <link href="clover/com/panorama/startup/impl/pkg-summary.html">code coverage report</link>
  shows, you can reach very high levels of code coverage (and code <em>confidence</em>) using unit tests.
</p>
  
  
</section>


  </body>
</document>
